Guide to the Papers of the Williams Family 1739-1842 (Bulk 1747-1770) MS 698
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Williams Family Papers
1739 - 1842 (Bulk 1747-1770)
MS 698
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.75 Linear feet (2 boxes)
A collection of correspondence, military records, legal documents, estate papers, receipts, accounts, invoices, inventories and personal items belonging to various members of the Williams family of Deerfield, Massachusetts, and other New England towns. Most of the collection involves Dr. Thomas Williams, his wife Esther, his brother Col. Ephraim Williams, his father-in-law Rev. William Williams, his son Solomon Williams, their relatives, friends and associates. Much of the correspondence and military material is dated 1755-1756 and relates to military expeditions in the Lake George, New York, area during the French and Indian Wars.
Provenance
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.) Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading room for details.
Biographical Note
1607 Birth of Robert Williams (1607-1693) who, with his wife Elizabeth Stalham (1597-1694) began this New England Williams line. The materials within the collection primarily involve the descendants of his sons Isaac (1638-1707) and Samuel (1632-1698) who married sisters Martha Parke (1641-1674) and Theoda Parke (1637-1718).
1664 Birth of John Williams, son of Samuel Williams (1632-1698) and Theoda Parke (1637-1718). John Williams (1664-1729), one of the most well known members of the Williams family, was an ordained minister and an early settler of Deerfield, Massachusetts. He lost his first wife, Eunice Mather, and two of his children in the Indian raid known as the Deerfield Massacre (1704) and was held in captivity in Canada for two years before returning to Deerfield. He married Abigail Bissell and one of their daughters, Abigail (1708-1787), married Col. Ebenezer Hinsdale (1706-1763). Hinsdale estate papers are included in this collection.
1688 Birth of William Williams, son of William Williams, Sr. (1664-1741) and Elizabeth Cotton (d. 1698). William Williams (1688-1760) is the author of many of the letters within this collection. He was a minister and the father of six children (several others died in infancy). Some of his children are represented in the correspondence: Esther Williams (1726-1800) who married Dr. Thomas Williams (see below); William Williams (1713-1788); and Anna Williams, whose husband, Oliver Partridge, is also represented in a number of letters. All of William's children are mentioned in his will, which is among the papers.
1706 Birth of Ebenezer Hinsdale. Ebenezer Hinsdale (1706-1763) was the son of Mehuman Hinsdale (1673-1736), said to be the first white child born in Deerfield. Mehuman's father, Samuel (1643-1675), was killed in the Indian raid known as the Bloody Brook Massacre (1675), and Mehuman was captured by Indians twice. Ebenezer was ordained as a missionary but had more success in military and business enterprises. He founded Hinsdale, New Hampshire, and build Fort Hinsdale. He served in the French and Indian Wars. His marriage to Abigail Williams, daughter of Rev. John Williams, formed the connection between the Hinsdales and the Williams family.
1713 Birth of John Hinsdale. John Hinsdale (1713-1746), son of Mehuman Hinsdale and brother of Col. Ebenezer Hinsdale, was another of the Hinsdales of Deerfield. The Hinsdale family was one of the wealthiest in Deerfield. Samuel Hinsdale (1641-1675), one of the first settlers and grandfather of John Hinsdale, owned 1/12 of the entire 8,000 acre grant originally set aside for settling the Pocumtuck territory (later becoming Deerfield, MA). Papers relating to John Hinsdale's estate are included in this collection.
1715 Birth of Ephraim Williams, son of Ephraim Williams, Sr. (1691-1754) and Elizabeth Jackson (d. 1718). Ephraim Williams (1715-1755) has a significant presence within this collection. Correspondence, his will and various other papers are included. Ephraim Williams was the founder of Williams College in Massachusetts; he lived in Stockbridge, Hatfield and Deerfield and had a notable career in the military. He was a commissioned officer as the continuing conflict between England and France erupted in King George's War (1745-1748) and the French and Indian War (1754-1763). He was captain of a company raised for the invasion of Canada in 1746, became major in 1753 and then colonel of the Hampshire troops. He was killed leading his regiment on the "Bloody Morning Scout," September 8, 1755, near Lake George.
1718 Birth of Thomas Williams, son of Ephraim Williams, Sr. (1691-1754) and Elizabeth Jackson (d. 1718). Much of the correspondence and many of the other papers included in this collection involve Dr. Thomas Williams (1718-1775) and his immediate family. A physician, Dr. Williams also participated in several military campaigns. In addition, he served in a number of local government positions. George Sheldon, in his 1895 book A History of Deerfield Massachusetts, writes that Williams "came to Deerfield in 1789; became a prominent figure as a man of affairs, as well as in his profession; was surgeon in the abortive Canadian expedition 1746 and for the line of forts; he left Fort Mass. only two days before its capture in 1746; was surgeon in the regt. of his brother Ephraim, at the battle of Lake George, Sept. 8, 1755 and dressed the wounds of Baron Dieskau, the captured commander of the Fr. army; in the campaign of 1756 he was lieut.-col.; rep 2 yrs; selectman 2; town clerk 17; judge of probate and justice of the court of common pleas; and had an extensive professional practice." Dr. Williams married Anna Childs in 1740 and three children were born before her death in 1746. He then married Esther Williams, the daughter of his cousin, Rev. William Williams (1688-1760). They had eleven children, although three died in infancy.
1764 Birth of Solomon Williams, son of Dr. Thomas Williams (1718-1775) and Esther Williams (1726-1800). Solomon Williams (1764-1836) is represented in this collection both in correspondence and in papers related to his position as town clerk and "Collector of the Direct Tax."
(Williams family trees are available in the repository.)
Additional sources of information include the following volumes, available in the library at the New-York Historical Society:
Andrews, Herbert Cornelius. Hinsdale Genealogy: Descendants of Robert Hinsdale of Dedham, Medfield, Hadley and Deerfield. Lombard, Ill: A.H. Andrews, 1906.
Sheldon, George. A History of Deerfield, Massachusetts: The Times When and the People by Whom it was Settled, Unsettled and Resettled. Deerfield, Mass., [Greenfield, Mass., Press of E.A. Hall & Co.] 1895-96.
Williams, Edward Higginson. Robert Williams of Roxbury, Mass., and His Descendants Four Generations. Newport, R.I., 1891.
Scope and Content Note
The descendants of Robert Williams (1607-1693) and Elizabeth Stalham (1597-1674) were a prestigious group whose members were social, economic, political, military and intellectual leaders. A great number were physicians, clergymen, or lawyers and many held positions of civic responsibility. Several had distinguished military careers. The founding of Williamstown, Massachusetts, and establishment of Williams College are among their accomplishments. William Williams (1731-1811), great great grandson of Robert Williams, was among the signers of the Declaration of Independence.
Members of the Williams family were among the earliest settlers of Deerfield, Massachusetts. Much has been written about Deerfield's Indian raids - the Bloody Brook Massacre in 1675 and the Deerfield Massacre, 1704 -- including several narratives concerning the capture of Reverend John Williams and his immediate family. The Redeemed Captive Returning to Zion (1707) was written by Rev. Williams describing his experiences in captivity. The Unredeemed Captive: A Family Story from Early America, written by John Demos in 1994, tells the story of Eunice Williams, John Williams' daughter, who chose to remain with her Indian captors.
The bulk of this collection falls during the time of the wars between the British and the French. Much of the correspondence and many of the papers involve military activity, some during King George's War (1745-1748) but most during the French and Indian War (1754-1763), especially the campaigns at Lake George and Crown Point.
There are 143 letters within the collection, the majority either written or received by Dr. Thomas Williams (1718-1775). Other materials include military papers; wills and other estate papers; inventories; surveys; receipts, notes and bills; deeds and other legal documents; medical papers; poetry and miscellaneous personal items.
Condition of the various items is mixed. Some are sturdy and legible while others are very fragile, torn, missing pieces or difficult to read. The collection has been microfilmed.
Arrangement
Series I. Correspondence (1747-1842, undated)
Series II. Military Documents (1748-1790, undated)
Series III. Receipts, Promissory Notes and Bills (1745-1797, undated)
Series IV. Wills and Estate Papers (1746-1806, undated)
Series V. Legal Material (1741-1810, undated)
Series VI. Survey and Plan (1739, 1761)
Series VII. Medical Inventories and Recipes (1748-1763, undated)
Series VIII. Poetry (undated)
Series IX. Personal Items and Notes (1693-1741, undated)
Most of the items in this collection were, at one time, assigned numbers (top left-hand corner of documents) and arranged within groups of numeric sequences. To facilitate access and utilization, however, a new arrangement has been imposed with series based on category of document. See Series Descriptions for arrangement of each.
This collection has been microfilmed. The arrangement of the film matches neither the old collection arrangement nor the new. Its sequence is outlined in the Microfilm Guide located at the end of the Container List.
The Williams Family Papers have been arranged into the following series:
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
This collection, along with several of the items mentioned below, is available on microfilm ( Williams, of Deerfield). See Microfilm Guide at the end of this document for sequence of items, as it does not follow the same arrangement as the collection itself.
Further information on the Williams family can be found in the following titles available in the New-York Historical Society library's collections:
Andrews, Herbert Cornelius. Hinsdale Genealogy: Descendants of Robert Hinsdale of Dedham, Medfield, Hadley and Deerfield. Lombard, Ill: A.H. Andrews, 1906. (Call Number: CS71.H665 no. 5)
Sheldon, George. A History of Deerfield, Massachusetts: The Times When and the People by Whom it was Settled, Unsettled and Resettled. Deerfield, Mass., [Greenfield, Mass., Press of E.A. Hall and Co.] 1895-96.(Call Number: F74.D4 S497)
Williams, Edward Higginson. Robert Williams of Roxbury, Mass., and His Descendants Four Generations. Newport, R.I., 1891. (Call Number: CS71.W72 no. 9)
The Library's Broadsides collection contains at least one item transferred from the Williams Family Papers:
Shirley's Orders for enlistment for the [Louisburg] expedition. Boston, 1755. (Call Number: S P1755-4)
Several bound volumes exist in the Manuscript Department:
Account Book and Daybook, 1785-1836 - Call Phrase: BV Williams, Solomon
List of the Inhabitants of Deerfield, Massachusetts, with Amount of Tax Paid by Each, 1800-1801 - Call Phrase: BV Williams, Solomon
Account Books and Blotter, 1749-1797 - Call Phrase: BV Williams, Thomas
Sermons, 1708-1746 - Call Phrase: BV Williams, William
Dwight, Abigail; Dwight, Joseph; Great Britain. Army--Colonial forces--Massachusetts; Great Britain. Army--Colonial forces--New York (State); Hinsdale family; Hinsdale, John,--Estate; Partridge, Oliver; Pynchon, Charles; Shattuck, Oliver, 1751-1797; Williams, Ephraim, 1715-1755; Williams, Esther, 1726-1800; Williams, Thomas, 1718-1775; Williams, William, 1665-1746; Williams, William, 1713-1788; Williams, Williams, 1688-1760; Catechisms; Clergy; Correspondence; Crown Point Expedition, 1755; Decedent's estates--Massachusetts; Deerfield (Mass.); Estate inventories; George, Lake, Battle of, 1755; Massachusetts--Social life and customs--To 1775; Medicine--Practice--Massachusetts; Military records; Muster rolls; New York (State)--History--French and Indian War, 1755-1763; Officers (military officers); Physicians; Poems; Recipes; Returns (military reports); United States--History--French and Indian War, 1755-1763; Williamstown (Mass.); Wills
- Series I. Correspondence (1747-1842, undated)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains 143 letters, the majority either received or written by Dr. Thomas Williams (1718-1775). In many of the letters he is referred to as Col. Williams, as they were written during his service as a military surgeon. Box 1, Folders 1 through 3 contain letters written to Dr. Williams from a variety of family members, military associates, physicians and others. Box 1, Folder 4 contains a series of letters written to Dr. Williams and his wife, Esther, by her father Rev. William Williams (1688-1760) who was Thomas's father-in-law and his cousin. In Box 1, Folder 5 are letters written to Esther Williams. The first sixteen are from her husband, written mostly while he was serving in the military. Letters written to Col. Ephraim Williams are contained in Box 1, Folder 7. Dr. Thomas Williams' son, Solomon, is the recipient of letters in Box 1, Folder 8. The final folder in this series contains letters to and from other Williams family members and associates. It is difficult to ascertain the recipient of some of the items.
  Among the many letters of interest in this series are those that provide first-hand accounts of military activity during the French and Indian War. Two items in Box 1, Folder 8, written in March of 1842 by Dr. Stephen W. Williams (grandson of Dr. Thomas Williams), contain copies of a number of letters that fall into this category. In one, Dr. Williams tells his wife about the September 8, 1755, ambush (Early Morning Scout) and the death of his brother Ephraim, as well as the continuing battle at Lake George and capture of the French Baron Dieskau. Given his responsibilities as surgeon, he is able to describe the wounds sustained by many individual soldiers. Most of the other letters written in 1755 and 1756 also contain accounts of military action. A letter in Box 1, Folder 6, written by William Williams to Col. Ephraim Williams on September 2 (six days before Ephraim's death), includes a discussion of Ephraim's will along with comments about the state of the ongoing war.
  A letter in Box 1, Folder 8, written August 22, 1755, to Monsieur St. Luke Lacorn by John Hawks, asks for help in locating captives in Canada. Several of the items mention smallpox and smallpox inoculation (Box 1, Folder 3, January 1765, #95 and Box 1, Folder 5, December 1776, #104). There is a letter in Box 1, Folder 8 written on July 11, 1750 to "the Gentlemen assembled at Deerfield" regarding a complaint against Ebenezer Hinsdale who was accused of intemperance.
  Other letters focus on family, financial and personal affairs, health and illness issues, and local news. Many are filled with religious reflections, particularly those sent by Rev. William Williams.
  Within each folder, the letters are arranged chronologically. The condition of the items is mixed. Many are fragile, some torn or missing pieces. Legibility is good in most cases.
  - Letters Received by Dr. Thomas Williams (1 of 3), 1748-1754 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters Received by Dr. Thomas Williams (2 of 3), 1755 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters Received by Dr. Thomas Williams (3 of 3), 1756-1775 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters Received by Dr. Thomas Williams and Esther Williams from Rev. William Williams, 1748-1759 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters Received by Esther Williams, 1747-1795 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters Received by Col. Ephraim Williams, 1754-1755 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters Received by Solomon Williams, 1778-1821, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Other Williams Family Letters, 1747-1842, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II. Military Documents (1748-1790, undated)
  Because most members of the Williams family were active participants in the French and Indian War, military documents make up a significant portion of this collection. Box 1, Folder 9, for example, contains 57 enlistment papers from March and April of 1756, all slated for the Crown Point expedition. Mentioned among the leadership of the expedition are Thomas Williams, Elijah Williams, William Williams and Joseph Dwight. The enlistment papers are in good condition and have been arranged in alphabetic order by last name of enlistee.
  In Box 1, Folder 10 are more materials from the Crown Point action. They include items such as Thomas Williams' commission as Lt. Col. and Captain of "a Regiment of Foot" in the British army of Massachusetts Bay province, dated September 9, 1755. Also contained in the folder are troop rosters, muster rolls, pay receipts, calculation sheets, lists of accounts and a variety of notes. The items are arranged in chronological order. Many are not dated; they have been placed last in the folder.
  Military papers in Box 1, Folder 12 include such items as pay documents for the troops of Capt. Ephraim Williams (1749-1750); a list of sick and wounded (October 12, 1755); a list of "articles of plunder" (October 14, 1755); and a copy of Montcalm's Articles of Capitulation, allowing for the retreat of Monroe's troops and their dependents from Fort William Henry to Fort Edward (September 9, 1757). Items are arranged chronologically.
  - French and Indian War Papers - Enlistments and Returns, 1756 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - French and Indian War Papers - Crown Point Expedition, 1755-1756, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Captain Oliver Shattucks Company Payroll, 1781-1782 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Other Military Papers, 1748-1790, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series III. Receipts, Promissory Notes and Bills (1745-1797, undated)
  Series III is composed of two folders, each containing receipts, invoices, promissory notes, accounts and various brief notes. The items are arranged in chronological order; those not dated are placed at the end of the series.
  - Receipts, Notes and Bills (1 of 2), 1745-1760 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Receipts, Notes and Bills (2 of 2), 1761-1797, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series IV. Wills and Estate Papers (1746-1806, undated)
  Series IV is composed of wills and related estate papers. In Box 1, Folder 15 are an unsigned version and a copy of the will of Col. Ephraim Williams written on July 22, 1755, as he awaited major military action. He died less than two months later, on September 8. After bequests to members of his family, he left the remainder of his estate to support and maintain "a free school in the township west of Fort Massachusetts." This area later became Williamstown and the school, Williams College.
  Other wills, those of Thomas Williams and William Williams, are contained in Box 1, Folder 16, along with estate inventory lists, an official appointment by the probate judge to inventory Thomas Williams' estate, and a transfer of land out of Thomas Williams' estate by Esther Williams.
  Hinsdale family estate documents are found in Box 1, Folder 17. They primarily involve two sons of Mehuman Hinsdale (1673-1736) and his wife, Mary (1680-1763). The sons, John Hinsdale (1713-1746) and Ebenezer Hinsdale (1706-1763), both had significant estates and, since John's death preceded Ebenezer's, portions of John's estate became involved in the estate of Ebenezer. The Hinsdale and Williams families were joined through the marriage of Ebenezer to Abigail Williams, daughter of Rev. John Williams (1664-1729). Another family member whose estate is included in this series is Abigail Norton (1745-1806), daughter of John Hinsdale and a favorite niece of Abigail Williams Hinsdale.
  - Will of Col. Ephraim Williams, 1755 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Williams Family Wills and Estate Papers, 1755-1789, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hinsdale Family Estate Papers, 1746-1806, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Series V. Legal Material (1741-1810, undated)
  Williams family members served in a number of civic positions. Dr. Thomas Williams, for example, held a number of offices including Justice of the Peace; William Williams, town clerk; and Solomon Williams, Collector of the Direct Tax. Series V contains a variety of legal items including court actions and governmental body papers.
  The official appointment of Thomas Williams to the position of Justice of the Peace may be found in Box 2, Folder 1. Among the items of interest in Box 2, Folder 2, is the testimony of William Symmes regarding the drunkenness of Col. Ebenezer Hinsdale (July, 1750). A series of court judgments settling the debts of one William Barnard, "absent and absconding debtor," who owed money to Esther Williams and John Williams, among others (1791) and a draft (1810) of a business partnership involving Henry Williams are also included. Most of the deeds contained in Box 2, Folder 3, were signed by Thomas Williams in his official capacity. Solomon Williams' tax collection instructions and reports may be found in Box 2, Folder 4. Solomon (1764-1836) was the son of Thomas.
  Box 2, Folder 5 contains several local government documents, one of which is a copy of a resolution passed by the Provisional Congress of Watertown on May 8, 1775, concerning disarmament of those who remain loyal to Britain and are considered "Enemies to the Rights of Mankind and the Interest of America."
  Materials in this series are arranged chronologically and most are in fair to good condition.
  - Thomas Williams - Justice of the Peace Appointment, 1762 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Agreements, Bonds, Judgments and Testimony, 1741-1810, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Deeds, 1765-1778 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Tax Collection Documents, 1800-1801 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Governmental Body Papers, 1762-1775 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series VI. Survey and Plan (1739, 1761)
  A 1739 survey of a 250 acre plot of land near Deerfield, Massachusetts, and the 1761 plan of New Framington, Berkshire County, are included in this series.
  - Survey and Plan, 1739, 1761 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series VII. Medical Inventories and Recipes (1748-1763, undated)
  Box 2, Folder 7 contains several medicinal recipes -- an 'approved medicine for the jaundice' containing earthworms, and a 'diet drink.' There are also a number of medical item inventories and invoices including an account of the medicines supplied to Brig. Gen. Dwight's Regiment in 1746. Most of the items belonged to Dr. Thomas Williams. The recipes in Box 2, Folder 8 are non-medicinal - 'a white fricuse of chickins' and 'To Dress Veal A la mode.'
  - Medical Inventories and Recipes, 1748-1763, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Recipes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series VIII. Poetry (undated)
  The collection contains several items of poetry including an "Ode to Gen'l Wolfe" and an 'eloqium' on the bravery of the men at the Battle of Lake George with reference to the death of Ephraim Williams. These materials are not dated.
  - Poetry, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series IX. Personal Items and Notes (1693-1741, undated)